In our last tale
En nuestra última historia
Rex Lapis was walking alone in the mountains
Rex Lapis caminaba en solitario por las montañas.
He heard a remote voice unlike any other
Escuchó una voz lejana e insólita
Coming from a crack in the earth
que venía de una grieta en el suelo.
Most of the ancient Geo life forms that live below Liyue are blind
La mayoría de criaturas Geo antiguas que viven bajo Liyue son ciegas.
Having not seen the sunlight for an age
No han visto la luz del sol en miles de años.
The voice was sometimes sad and songlike, other times it was loud and thunderous
Esa voz a veces era como una canción lúgubre
The Lord of Geo searched here and there
El Rey Geo buscó por todos lados
Before finally unearthing a strange stone from the bedrock
hasta dar con una extraña piedra bajo una formación rocosa.
That's how Azhdaha was
Se trataba de Azhdaha.
I answered his wish, and took him above ground
Respondí a su deseo y lo traje a la superficie.
The Lord of Geo took pity on the rock's spirit
El Rey Geo se apiadó del espíritu de la piedra
And carved it into a magnificent work of craftsmanship — a vivid representation of a dragon
y en ella esculpió una majestuosa obra de arte:
I bestowed him with a pair of eyes to see the world
Le concedí ojos para que viera el mundo
And came to an agreement with him
e hice un trato con él.
With his fingers, he made two eyes
Con sus dedos, esculpió dos ojos a gran velocidad.
And a living, breathing dragon soared into the clouds!
¡y un dragón de carne y hueso ascendió a las nubes!
I agreed to let him live among the people above ground
Le permití vivir en la superficie con la gente
But if the day ever came when he brought ruin to order
pero si llegara el día en que perturbara el orden
He would once again be sealed in the dark
sería sellado nuevamente en la oscuridad.
The dragon accompanied the Lord of Geo
El dragón acompañó al Rey Geo
Fighting campaigns alongside him in the four corners of the world
en sus luchas a lo largo y ancho del mundo.
We have a saying to eulogize these events:
Tenemos un proverbio para elogiar estos acontecimientos:
"The crash of a spear brought billowing dust"
“El polvo se alzó al golpe de una lanza
"The mountains and waters made way at the sound"
montañas y aguas dieron paso al sonido”.
"The sight of a dragon bestowed with a touch"
“Un dragón abrió camino al agua
"The promise of rainwater blessing the ground"
con una gran lluvia en las tierras que él bendijo”.